# Nicholas Muchelemba

Lusaka, 10101 | +260971442814 | nmuchelemba60@gmail.com

#### CAREER OBJECTIVE

Knowledgeable Software Developer with in-depth knowledge of Java, C# JavaScript, Python and PHP. Skilful in developing, optimizing and reworking systems to meet specific customer requirements. Expertise in writing codes in various languages, developing flowcharts and layouts and integrating software components.

#### CORE COMPETENCIES

- Fluent in Java, Python, C#,PHP
- SQL expert
- Drone Programming
- Web development

- Computer Vision
- Project management
- Blazor and Asp.net
- Data Science and AI

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **First Quantum Minerals**

Software Developer, April 2021 – Present

- Developing and designing mining compliance application in Blazor with a Sql server database.
- Designing reports in power bi.
- Task Automation using python.
- Machine learning to enhance data prediction of mining BCMs.

## **National Institute of Public Administration**

Software Developer, Oct 2020 – April 2021

- Developing and designing the Online registration module, to be integrated on student management system.
- Implemented and tested features requested to improve product functionality and extend performance.
- Designed user-friendly software interfaces to simplify overall management.
- Introduced automation tools to reduce redundancy and enhance workflow.
- Technologies used include: PHP, JavaScript, Java, JSP, Python. 2 Automate tasks using python

## **Global Drone Academy**

Software Engineer/Drone Instructor (part time), Jul 2020-Apr 2021

- Writing Python scripts to automate the drone operation.
- Training students on how to safely fly drones and the safely regulation related to drone operation.
- Training students on how to build drones.

## **Zambia Industrial Commercial Bank**

Information Technology Intern, Aug 2020 – Oct 2020

- Digitized User Request and Change Request Systems using ASP.net core (C#).
- Provide support, Error Tracing, Log management Database Administration on the Oracle Database Platform.
- Manage and provide support for Sea Bank Reports (System) Support and manage IT support
- integration with Jira service desk
- Kept software patched and licenses up to date.
- Increased number of resolved job tickets by 50% over previous year.

## **Bluekey Seidor Zambia**

Software Engineer Intern, Jul 2019 - Sep 2019

- Developed an Android prototype application to support the users of SAP business one transport add-on.
- Modified the installer for SAP to reduce installation complexity by 60%.
- Provided SAP support service to clients remotely, this included updating, Database Migration, I installation and licensing.

## **EDUCATION**

## Mulungushi University Kabwe

Bachelor of Science: Computer Science, Nov 2020

- Summa cum laude (**Distinction**) graduate
- Best Graduating Student Recipient
- Dissertation: Crop disease detection using machine learning
- ICTAZ Member
- ICTAZ Mulungushi University Chapter Vic President

## **CERTIFICATION**

☑ Huawei Certification (Routing & Switching HCIA): valid through January 14 2023 ☑
Responsive Web Design (FreeCode Camp)

## ADDITIONAL SKILLS

- Unity Game Developer
- Drone pilot and drone Instructor (Global Air Drone Academy)

# WEBSITES, PORTFOLIOS, PROFILES

☐ https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicholas-muchelemba/ ☐
https://nicholas124.github.io/NicholasMuchelemba/

## REFERENCES

## Mining Engineer - First Quantum mining Operation(FQMO)

• Name: Mr Niza Mwasile

Tel: +260962890718/0976607529Email: Niza.Mwasile@fqml.com

## Senior Software Developer (Supervisor) - National Institute of Public Administration(NIPA)

• Name: Mr Alinaswe Siame

Tel: +260978614927

• Email: alinaswe.siame@nipa.ac.zm

## Head of Department Computer Science - National Institute of Public Administration(NIPA)

Name: Dr Christopher Chembe Phd.

Tel: +260972890297

• **Email**: cchembe@nipa.ac.zm

## Manager Information Technology (Supervisor) - Zambia Industrial Commercial Bank

Name: Mr Funwell Malake

Tel: +260966855355

• Email: Funwell.Malake@zicb.co.zm

## Chief executive officer (CEO) (Supervisor) - Bluekey Seidor Zambia

Name: Mupota Muchelemba

Tel: + 260967783283

Email: <u>mupota@gmail.com</u>

## Co-founder (Supervisor) - Global Drone Academy

Name: Mr Eno Umoh

Tel: + 1 443-986-7503/+234-902-020-6099

Email: eumoh@gadacademy.org